Guide to the Coleman O. Parsons Papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Coleman O. Parsons Papers,
1716-1981
Parsons, Coleman O., 1905-
3 linear ft., (ca.1,600 items, 7 boxes)
Columbia University Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4078544
Biographical Note
Coleman O. Parsons, 1905-. (Columbia A.B., 1928). Professor of English, City University of New York; book collector.
Scope and Content
Letters, manuscripts, notes, memorabilia, photographs, and printed material. Cataloged letters from George Colman the Elder, English dramatist; Lord Jeffrey, Scottish judge and critic; Andrew Lang, Scottish author; Robert Montgomery, English poet; Richard Parsons Rosse,1st Earl of Rosse; George Thomson, friend of Robert Burns and music editor; Bernard De Voto, critic, and S.R. Crockett, Scottish author. Cataloged manuscripts by Thomas Campbell, Scottish poet, James Montgomery, and E.I. Powell. Cataloged diaries of June and Coleman O. Parsons of their trip around the world in 1936-37. There are also ca.700 pages of notes by Coleman O. Parsons on various Scottish authors(including Sir Walter Scott), Scottish folk-lore and history, and Scottish poetry. Most of the notes concern his research on Francis Colman, George Colman the Elder, and George Colman the Younger. In addition there is the mss. for his book "Studies in Eccentricity"; the mss. of an 18th century Scottish ghost story entitled "A Cool Dialogue between the Living and the Dead" and notes and essays on Mark Twain, as well as a poetry album kept by Elizabeth Saynor Marshall and photographs of Parsons in South Africa.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 6 series:
Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
Series II: Cataloged Manuscripts
Series III: Cataloged Objects
Series IV: Arranged Correspondence
Series V: Arranged Manuscripts
Series VI: Printed Materials
Subjects
Crockett, S. R. (Samuel Rutherford), 1860-1914.; Marshall, Elizabeth Saynor.; Scott, Walter, Sir, 1771-1832.; Twain, Mark, 1835-1910.; Scotland--Description and travel.; Lake District (England)--Description and travel.; Scottish literature.; Eccentrics and eccentricities.; Ghost stories, Scottish--18th century.; Albums.; Diaries.; Poems.; Book collectors.--United States--20th century.; College teachers.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: 3-7. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
12/05/1986 M-86-12-05 Parsons, Coleman O. Gift
1984 M-1984 Album of E.S. Marshall Parsons, Colman O. Gift
Gift of Coleman O. Parsons, 1986 & 1989.
Gift of Goleman O. Parsons, 1979, 1984, 1986, & 1989.
- Series I: Cataloged Correspondence
  - Crockett, Samuel Rutherford, 1860-1914 (Box 1)
  - Colman, George, 1732-1794 (Box 1)
  - De Voto, Bernard (Box 1)
  - Jeffrey, Francis Jeffrey, Lord, 1773-1850 (Box 1)
  - Lang, Andrew, 1844-1912 (Box 1)
  - Montgomery, Robert, 1807-1855 (Box 1)
  - Rosse, Richard Parsons, 1st Earl of, d.1741 (Box 1)
  - Thomson, George, 1757-1851 (Box 1)
- Series II: Cataloged Manuscripts
  - Bürger, Gottfried August, 1748-1794 (Box 1)
  - Campbell, Thomas, 1777-1844 (Box 1)
  - Montgomery, James, 1771-1854 (Box 1)
  - Parsons, Coleman O. (Box 1)
  - Parsons, June Lee. (Box 1)
  - Powell, E I (Box 2)
- Series III: Cataloged Objects
  - Scott, Sir Walter. Lock of Sir Walter Scott's hair., [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 2)
- Series IV: Arranged Correspondence
  - Correspondence, A-Z, [v.p.], [v.d.] (Box 2)
- Series V: Arranged Manuscripts
  - Plays, [v.p.], [v.d.] (Box 2)
    [Many with Coleman Parson's notes.]
  - George Colman the Elder Entertainment of Harlequin Teague, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 2)
  - George Colman the Elder. The Enraged Musician, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 2)
  - George Colman the Elder. The Genius of Nonsense, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 2)
  - George Colman the Elder. The Jealous Wife, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 2)
  - George Colman the Elder. Preludio, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 2)
  - George Colman the Elder. Prologues and Epilogues, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 2)
  - George Colman the Elder. The Separate Maintenance, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 2)
  - George Colman the Elder. Sheep Shearing, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 2)
  - George Colman the Elder. The Spanish Barber, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 2)
  - George Colman the Elder. The Spleen, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 2)
  - George Colman the Elder. The Suicide, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 2)
  - George Colman the Elder. Tit for Tat, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 2)
  - Marshall, Elizabeth Saynor Poetry Album, [n.p.], [1849-1946], (72 leaves in, 1 volume) (Box 3)
  - Parsons, Coleman. Bibliography of eighteenth century plays and literature., [n.p.], [n.d.], (ca. 150 index cards) (Box 3)
  - [?] "A Cool Dialogue between the Living and the Dead.", [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 3)
    [An unidentified ghost story.]
  - Essays and Articles., [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 3)
  - Lecture on Sir Walter Scott., [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 3)
  - Lecture " " by an itinerant boarder speaker., [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 3)
  - Notes and essays on Mark Twain., [n.p.], [n.d.], (3 folders) (Box 3)
    [Includes and autobiographical sketch of Coleman Parsons.]
  - Notes on the Aberdeen Journal., [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 3)
  - Notes on the Coleman family., [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 3)
  - Notes on Thomas Campbell., [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 3)
  - Notes on William Chambers., [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 3)
  - Notes on Francis Colman, George Colman the Elder and George Colman the Younger, [n.p.], [n.d.], (19 folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-19)
  - Notes on Francis Colman, George Colman the Elder and George Colman the Younger., [n.p.], [n.d.], (16 folders) (Box 5, Folder 20-36)
  - Notes on Eighteenth century plays, [n.p.], [n.d.], (14 folders) (Box 6)
    [ Many with texts of the plays]
  - Notes on George (Gordon), Duke of Gordon, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 6)
  - Notes on George Hogarth, 1783-187, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 6)
  - Notes on Baron Lyndhurst, Lord Chancellor., [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 6)
  - Notes on James Montgomery, 1771-1854., [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 6)
  - Notes on Robert Montgomery, 1807-1855., [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 6)
  - Notes on Julia Pardoe, 1806-1862., [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 6)
  - Notes on Scottish folklore and poetry., [n.p.], [n.d.], (6 folders) (Box 6)
  - Notes on George Thomson, 1757-1851., [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 6)
  - Short stories, [n.p.], [n.d.], (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - "Studies in Eccentricity.", [n.p.], [n.d.], (11 folders) (Box 7)
  - Two notebooks detailing trans-Atlantic trips by an unidentified author., [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 7)
  - Photocopies of letters and manuscripts. [v.p.], [v.p.], [n.d.] (Box 7)
  - Photographs of Coleman Parsons, South Africa, [n.d.] (Box 7)
- Series VI: Printed Materials
  - Clippings relating to Mark Twain, [n.p.], [v.d.] (Box 7)
  - Clippings (photographs of Mark Twain), [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 7)
  - An Excerpt from the General Catalogue of Printed Books in the British Museum re. Daniel Defoe, England, 1953 (Box 7)
  - "Notes and Queries.", [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 7)
  - Offprint from "The Review of English Studies.", [n.p.], {n.d.] (Box 7)
  - Photocopies., [n.p.], [n.d.], (3 folders) (Box 7)
  - Two Odes by George Colman the Elder, [n.p.], [n.d.] (Box 7)